<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
    <header>
        <title>Beehive SVN Documentation</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <p>
        Welcome to Beehive!  Apache Beehive is a project focused on building ease-of-use frameworks for enterprise Java applications.  
        Using Java 5.0 annotations for configuration and declarative programming, Beehive reduces the amount of coding necessary for 
        building enterprise applications.
        </p>
        <p>
        Beehive consists of several projects which can be used either together or seprately depending on the requirements of an application.
        These include:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <strong>NetUI</strong>: A project that includes Page Flow and a powerful set of JSP tags.  Page Flow is
                an annotation-driven web application programming framework built on Struts, including
                first-class integration with JavaServer Faces and Struts itself.  It centralizes navigation logic,
                state, metadata, and exception handling in a single
                <a href="site:pageflow_overview">Page Flow Controller</a> class.  The NetUI JSP tag set is
                Page Flow-aware, and provides tags for rendering HTML / XHTML and higher-level UI constructs such as
                data grids and trees.
            </li>
            <li>
                <strong>Controls</strong>: A lightweight, metadata-driven component framework for building that reduces the 
                complexity of being a client of enterprise resources.  Controls provide a unified client abstraction that
                can be implemented to access a diverse set of enterprise resources using a single configuration model.
            </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
        In addition, Beehive includes a set of <em>system controls</em> that are abstractions for low-level J2EE resource APIs such
        as EJB, JMS, JDBC, and web services.
        </p>
        <p>
        The Beehive documentation package contains tutorials, user guies, samples, and project templates for getting started building
        various kinds of applications.  If you are new to Beehive, the overview documentation for NetUI and Controls are good starting
        points:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="site:docs/controls/overview">Controls</a></li>
            <li><a href="site:pageflow_overview">NetUI</a></li>
        </ul>
        <p>
        To get started building Beehive-enabled projects, follow the <a href="site:setup">Setup</a> instructions and look at the 
        Beehive <strong>project templates</strong> which are skeletons for building new Beehive-enabled web applications and control
        projects:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="site:netui-blank">Blank NetUI</a></li>
            <li><a href="site:control-blank">Blank Control</a></li>
        </ul>
        <p>
        More detailed information on starting projects is available in the <strong>getting started</strong> guides:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="site:docs/controls/getting_started">Controls</a></li>
            <li><a href="site:docs/pageflow/netuiIntro/getting_started">NetUI</a></li>
        </ul>
        <p>
        The <strong>tutorials</strong> are end-to-end examples of how to build projects with Beehive features:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="site:docs/controls/tutorial">Controls</a></li>
            <li><a href="site:docs/tutorials/pageflow">NetUI</a></li>
        </ul>
        <p>
        The <strong>samples</strong> are another good starting point for learning about Beehive.
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="site:petstore">Petstore Sample</a></li>
            <li><a href="site:netui-samples">NetuI Samples</a></li>
            <li><a href="site:netui-jsf">NetUI + JSF Integration</a></li>
        </ul> 
    </body>
    <footer>
        <legal>
        &copy; 2005, Apache Software Foundation
        </legal>
    </footer>
</document>
