<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
	"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
    <header>
        <title>HTLM and XHTML Support</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <section id="Intro">
             <title>Introduction</title>
             <p>The following topic explains the support for creating valid XHTML and HTML from the NetUI tags.
                 The NetUI tags currently support three levels of the XHTML and HTML specs, HTML 4.01 Loose
                 (Transitional DTD),
                 HTML 4.01 Loose Quirks mode and XHTML 1.0 Transitional.  By
                 default, the tags support HTML 4.01 Loose, Quirks mode.
             </p>
             <p> Future versions of NetUI may support HTML 4.01 Strict and XHTML Strict.  This is currently not
                 supported because
                 there are a number of visual presentation attributes supported by the NetUI HTML tags, which are not
                 supported by HTML 4.01 Strict DTD (for example &lt;netui:body>'s bgcolor attribute).  In order
                 to support these strict modes, the NetUI tags would need to report runtime errors when the deprecated
                 attributes are set.
             </p>
         </section>
         <section id="BasicStructure">
            <title>Basic Tag Structure</title>
            <p>The minimum JSP should be of the following structure:</p>
             <p><strong>Basic JSP</strong></p>
            <source><![CDATA[
<%@ page language="java" contentType="text/html;charset=UTF-8"%>
<%@ taglib prefix="netui" uri="http://beehive.apache.org/netui/tags-html-1.0"%>
<netui:html>
    <head>
        <title>Page Title</title>
        <netui:base/>
    </head>
    <netui:body>
    </netui:body>
</netui:html>
]]></source>
             <p> There are two primary tags that create the valid HTML structure and provide the core services of
                 the NetUI tag library, &lt;netui:html> and &lt;netui:body>.  These two tags are related to each
                 other.  Together they work together to create valid HTML.  The page above represents the typical
                 minimum page.  The <strong>html</strong> tag will output the HTML html element.  The &lt;head>
                 contains a title and the &lt;netui:base> tag which is used to locate resources and links on the page.
                 The <strong>body</strong> tag will then output the HTML body element.
             </p>
             <section id="HtmlTag">
                 <title>Html Tag</title>
                 <p> The &lt;netui:html> JSP tag typically acts as a top level container and in this role is responsible
                     for rendering the result of many of the core services of the tags. These services
                     include gathering up JavaScript and runtime errors and then renders them at the end of the page.
                     For more information on the Html tag see the
                     <a href="site:pageflow_tagsJavascript_ScriptContainer">ScriptContainers</a> topic.
                 </p>
                 <p> Typically if the html tag rendered this content it would be illegal
                     because the end tag &lt;/body> immediately precedes the &lt;/html> end tag and there is
                     no legal content allowed between these two end tags.  In order
                     to create legal HTML, the &lt;netui:body> tag defers to the Html tag to render content to the
                     generated page before the body end tag is rendered.  If the &lt;netui:body> tag is not present,
                     then the Html tag will render JavaScript and any runtime errors right before the &lt;/html> end
                     tag.
                 </p>
             </section>
             <section id="BodyTag">
                 <title>Body Tag</title>
                 <p> The &lt;netui:body> JSP tag will output the HTML body tag.  In addition, it works with the
                     &lt;netui:html> tag to render the JavaScript and runtime errors before the &lt;/body> end
                     tag.  In addition, it will also work with the &lt;netui:scriptBlock> tag to position any
                     JavaScript that must be positioned either before or after the framework generated JavaScript.
                     For more information see the <a href="site:pageflow_tagsJavascript_ScriptBlock">ScriptBlock</a>
                     information in the JavaScript Support topic.
                 </p>
             </section>
             <section id="ScriptBlockTag">
                 <title>ScriptBlock Tag</title>
                 <p> The primary role of the &lt;netui:scriptBlock> is to render HTML &lt;script> tags and position
                     JavaScript on the page in relationship to the framework generated JavaScript.
                     The ScriptBlock requires both the &lt;netui:html> and &lt;netui:body> tag to position the
                     output.  Without these two tags, the JavaScript is written out inline.
                     For more information see the <a href="site:pageflow_tagsJavascript_ScriptBlock">ScriptBlock</a>
                     information in the JavaScript Support topic.
                 </p>
             </section>
        </section>
        <section id="HtmlFormats">
            <title>Specifying the HTML Format</title>
            <p>This section describes the methods for setting the default HTML format for a WebApp.  Further, the
               format can be set on a JSP to override the WebApp default.
            </p>
            <section id="FormatIdentifiers">
                <title>Format Identifiers</title>
                <p> The Html tags currently support three HTML formats.  These are identified by the following
                    indentifier values:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><code>html4-loose</code> -- HTML 4.01 Transitional DTD (loose)</li>
                    <li><code>html4-loose-quirks</code> -- HTML 4.01 Transitional DTD, with Quirks mode turned on</li>
                    <li><code>xhtml1-transitional</code> -- XHTML 1.0 Transitional</li>
                </ul>
                <p> The identifier values are used set the HTML format in both the tags and in the configuration
                    file.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section id="WebAppFormat">
                <title>Setting the WebApp Format</title>
                <p> By default, all WebApps use <code>html4-loose-quirks</code> as the format.  In order
                    to override the default format, you set the WebApp default in the beehive-netui-config.xml.
                    The default is set by specifying the <a href="site:config_doctype">doctype</a> value inside
                    of the <code>jsp-tag-config</code> element.
                    For information on the NetUI Configuration file see the
                    <a href="site:netui_config">Reference Documentation: beehive-netui-config.xml File</a> topic.
                </p>
                <p> In the following example, the default format for the WebApp is changed to the HTML 4.01
                    Transitional DTD.  This value is found in the  beehive-netui-config.xml file.
                    The value of the &lt;doctype> element must be one of the values
                    specified above for the identifiers.
                </p>
                <source>
&lt;jsp-tag-config>
   &lt;doctype>html4-loose&lt;/doctype>
&lt;/jsp-tag-config>
</source>
            </section>
            <section id="DocumentFormat">
                <title>Setting the Document Format</title>
                <p> It is possible to override the HTML format on a document by document basis.  This is
                    done by setting the <strong>documentType</strong> of the &lt;netui:html> tag to one of the
                    identifiers above.  In the example below, the output format for the document will be
                    XHTML 1.0 Transitional.  It will override the default value for the WebApp.
                </p>
                <source>
&lt;%@ page language="java" contentType="text/html;charset=UTF-8"%>
&lt;%@ taglib uri="http://beehive.apache.org/netui/tags-html-1.0" prefix="netui"%>
&lt;netui:html documentType="xhtml1-transitional">
    ...
&lt;/netui:html>
</source>
            </section>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
